Inventory of the Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah [Iraq Memory Foundation] records
Hoover Institution Archives
Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah [Iraq Memory Foundation] records
2003-2010
2010C3
Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah
7 manuscript boxes and 1513 digital video files (2.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
File-based videorecordings, videocassettes, optical discs, and transcripts, as well as brochures and legal and financial records relating to political conditions and human rights violations in Iraq under the Ba'th party regime. Includes digitized video testimony of survivors.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research. While boxes 2-4 are closed, digital use copies of their contents are available. Boxes 5-7 closed until 2018 October 1. Use copies of most videorecordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009. An increment of videocassettes and optical discs was received in 2012, and an increment of administrative records was received in 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Hiẓb al-Ba'th al-'Arabī al-Ishtirākī in Iraq [Ba'th Arab Socialist Party of Iraq], Hoover Institution Archives
Kanan Makiya papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
The Mu'assasat al-dhākirah al-'Irāqīyah (Iraq Memory Foundation (IMF)) is a private nonprofit organization for documentation of Iraqi history under the Ba'th party regime. It was founded by Kanan Makiya in 1992 as the Iraq Research and Documentation Project (IRDP) at Harvard University's Center for Middle Eastern Studies. Makiya had just returned from a November 1991 trip to northern Iraq, where he viewed the archive of documents of the Hiẓb al-Ba'th al-'Arabଢ଼ al-Ishtirīkଢ଼ (Ba'th Arab Socialist Party of Iraq) that had been seized by Iraqi rebels. Makiya was accompanied by a BBC filmmaker who filmed his investigation of the Iraqi government's campaign of ethnic cleansing of Iraqi Kurds (the Anfal). The film, The Road to Hell, aired in January 1992 on BBC and then on PBS as a Frontline documentary under the title "Saddam's Killing Fields." Now president of the Iraq Memory Foundation, Makiya is the Sylvia Hassenfeld Professor of Modern Middle East Studies at Brandeis University. He has written many books, including Republic of Fear: The Politics of Modern Iraq (1989).
In 1993 the IRDP developed a plan to preserve the Ba'thist documents Makiya had examined in Iraq. Over the next ten years the IRDP received and processed documents and transcribed Iraqi refugee interviews.
After the fall of Saddam Hussein's regime in 2003, the IRDP relocated to Baghdad, where it registered as a Jam'iyah (society) in Iraq under the name Iraq Memory Foundation. It expanded its mission to include documenting all facets of the Iraqi experience under the regime of Saddam Hussein from 1968 to 2003. Also in 2003, the IMF acquired the Ba'th Regional Command collection from the basement of the Ba'th party headquarters in Baghdad.
The IMF began its Oral History on Film Project, which records the testimonies of witnesses to Ba'th regime repression, in 2003. Documentary filmmaker Mustafa Al-Kadhimiy, who formerly headed the Department of Programs and Planning at al-Iraqiyya television, led the project. In 2005, al-Iraqiyya began broadcasting ten-minute excerpts from the testimonies during prime time and they quickly became one of Iraq's top-rated TV programs. The IMF went on to produce several seasons of a series called Legacy of Evil for Iraqi television. This weekly program consists of interviews with witnesses, Saddam-era video footage, and presentations of documents created by the regime. In total, the IMF has more than 1700 hours of footage, including videos created by the Ba'th regime (now allocated to the Hiẓb al-Ba'th al-'Arabī al-Ishtirākī in Iraq records at Hoover), oral histories, the Legacy of Evil archive, and Saddam Hussein trial videorecordings. The IMF claims the copyrights on all the oral history videos it produces (IMF Prospectus 2008, page 26, box 1).
On September 21, 2005, IMF directors Kanan Makiya and Hassan Mneimneh testified before the human rights caucus of the U.S. Congress on the importance of the work of the IMF. The IMF also provided documents for use in the trial of Saddam Hussein.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection consists of materials created by the Iraq Memory Foundation (IMF) since its inception in 1992. Ba'th Party records collected by the IMF comprise a separate collection, the Hiẓb al-Ba'th al-'Arabī al-Ishtirākī in Iraq records.
IMF Database User Guide
IMF Video Guide
Arrangement
The collection is organized in five series, most of which were defined and named by the Iraq Memory Foundation: Printed matter, Videocassettes and optical discs, Video Documents Created by the Iraq Memory Foundation, Video Documents from Post 2003, and Administrative records.
All materials except the printed matter and administrative records are described in the "Video Documents" section of the searchable database designed and populated by the Iraq Memory Foundation. This database was acquired with the collection and is available at the Hoover Institution.
Database User Guide
Getting started with the IMF portal
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online public access catalog.
Civil rights--Iraq.; Iraq--History--1979-1991.; Iraq--History--1991-2003.; Hiẓb al-Ba'th al-'Arabī al-Ishtirākī (Iraq)
- Printed matter, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Prospectus 2008 (Box 1)
    Two copies, one Arabic, one English
- Video Documents Created by the Iraq Memory Foundation, 2003-2009
  - Iraqi Testimonies, 2003-2008; 1272 digital video files, 362 digital text files.
    Videorecordings of oral histories of 190 survivors of Ba'th Party repression.
    Two finding aids are available. One is descriptions of the interviewees from the Iraqi Testimonies DVD packaging, which are listed under Iraqi Testimonies video boxed sets, but relate to all of the Iraqi Testimonies series. These descriptions were taken essentially verbatim from this packaging (some spelling errors were corrected and some proper names were standardized to a single spelling).
    A second finding aid is the IMF database at the Hoover Institution, which can be searched by name of interviewee, with names entered in a mixture of Arabic and English. In the database, each name will include rushes (raw, unedited video footage of interviews, often several hours), the edited clip for broadcast on al-Iraqiyya television and distribution in DVD boxed sets, and a transcript of the broadcast video clip. Most individual files also include textual information including biographical information forms on the interviewee and a research form completed by IMF to verify the interviewee's story.
    A selection of the videos also includes a video clip with English subtitles. A list of these interviewees with descriptions is appended to this finding aid.
    - Iraqi Testimonies (Rushes), 2003-2008; 1071 digital video files (Workstation)
      File-based raw, unedited video footage of 190 interviews, sometimes from two cameras. Interviews may be 6 hours or longer, with each split into multiple video files. Access is by name of interviewee. In Arabic and Kurdish
    - Iraqi Testimonies, 2005-2008; 190 digital video files (Workstation)
      File-based video clips excerpted from the Iraqi Testimonies (Rushes) for broadcast on al-Iraqiyya television and distribution in DVD boxed sets.
      There is one clip for each of the 190 interviewees. Clips range from 5 to 15 minutes, with multiple clips combined in one video file. Access is by name of interviewee. In Arabic and Kurdish, with Arabic subtitles for Kurdish speakers
    - Iraqi Testimonies (with English subtitles), 2005; 2007-2008; 106 digital video files (Workstation)
      File-based video clips with English subtitles for 106 of the clips in the previous series, representing 106 interviewees. Access is by name of interviewee. In Arabic and Kurdish, with English subtitles
    - Iraqi Testimonies (Opening and closing titles), 2005; 2007-2008; 2 digital video files (Workstation)
      File-based video clips that begin and end the DVD versions.
    - Iraqi Testimonies (Transcripts), 2003-2008; 190 digital text files (Workstation)
      File-based transcripts of the 5-15 minute clips used for broadcast on al-Iraqiyya television and distribution in DVD boxed sets. In Arabic and Kurdish.
    - Iraqi Testimonies (Research files), 2003-2008; 172 digital text files (Workstation)
      File-based case files for 172 of the 190 interviewees include a research form created by IMF before the interviews were conducted. It contains biographical information and information on the accusation and experience of the individual, to verify the story told. In Arabic.
    - Iraqi Testimonies video boxed sets, 2005-2008; 21 discs/190 digital video file clips (Box 1 and Workstation)
      One hundred ninety video clips of survivors, including 100 clips with English subtitles, were distributed in DVD boxed sets, with packaging that includes a pamphlet describing each interviewee.
      In addition, 6 clips from the 2005 DVD set with English subtitles are available on an unpublished DVD (in AV room, with digital copies in IMF database). A 13-minute video profile of the IMF, in English, is included in the 2007 and 2008 DVD boxed sets.
      Arranged chronologically by publication year. In Arabic, Kurdish, and English (DVD use copies of boxed sets are also in AV room)
      - Discs 1-5, and one unpublished disc, 2005 (Box 1 and Workstation)
        40 oral history clips. Six of these testimonies, with English subtitles added, are available on an unpublished DVD (in AV room, with digital copies in IMF database). In Arabic, Kurdish, and English
      - Discs 1-5, 2006 (Box 1 and Workstation)
        50 oral history clips. In Arabic and Kurdish
      - Discs 1-5, 2007 (Box 1 and Workstation)
        In Arabic with English subtitles unless otherwise noted. See Appendix for descriptions and interviewee list.
      - Discs 1-5, 2008 (Box 1 and Workstation)
  - Legacy of Evil, 2006-2008; 34 digital video files/100 programs (Workstation)
    File-based videorecordings of the weekly Iraqi television program Legacy of Evil. The shows consist of interviews with witnesses, Saddam Hussein-era video footage, and presentations of documents of the Ba'th regime. Excerpts from Iraqi Testimonies were used in this program. Files range from 10 minutes to 3 hours in duration. In Arabic
    The IMF database at the Hoover Institution is the only finding aid; it can be searched by video description or title, which are entered in Arabic
  - Documentaries, 2009; 5 digital video files (Workstation)
    File-based video documentaries about the Saddam Hussein regime that incorporate interviews conducted by the IMF and Saddam Hussein-era video footage. Programs were created for various purposes. They range from 19 to 22 minutes in duration. In Arabic
    The IMF database at the Hoover Institution is the only finding aid; it can be searched by title, which is entered in Arabic
  - Iraq Memory Foundation Activities, 2003-2006; 14 digital video files (Workstation)
    6 videos are closed, but the descriptions of them in the IMF database are open.
    File-based videos of Saddam Hussein's trial before the Supreme Iraqi Criminal Tribunal, produced by Iraqi National TV. The files range from 4 minutes to more than 3 hours in duration, with the average about 40 minutes. In Arabic
    The IMF database at the Hoover Institution is the only finding aid; it can be searched by title, which is entered in Arabic, with part numbers listed in English
- Video Documents from Post 2003 collected by the IMF, 2003-2009; 243 digital video files
  10 videos are closed, but the descriptions of them in the IMF database are open.
  File-based videos were collected or given to the IMF after 2003, and were created after the end of Saddam Hussein's rule. They may also contain content recorded before 2003. The videos often include multiple clips on one recording, including news broadcasts, documentaries, speeches, parades, events, interrogations, and other material from many difference sources. Included are 136 recordings of Saddam Hussein's trial before the Supreme Iraqi Criminal Tribunal, produced by Iraqi National TV. In Arabic.
  The files range from 4 minutes to more than 3 hours in duration, with the average about 40 minutes.
  The IMF database at the Hoover Institution is the only finding aid; it can be searched by title, which is entered in Arabic, with part numbers listed in English. Two browsing options are available, serial numbers or broad topics, which were developed by the IMF. There are 22 broad topics:
  News and Documentaries
  Iraqi Testimonies
  Saddam Trials
  Individuals
  Private Events
  Looting
  Military Parade
  Torture (CLOSED)
  Mass Graves
  Religious
  Interrogation of Suspected Terrorist
  Events
  Saddam's Palaces
  Anfal
  Organizations
  North
  South
  Center
  East
  West
  Date
  Other
  Keyword searches of the database search the video title, description, date of subject matter, geographic names, corporate names, and specific subjects supplied by the IMF. Topical fields are in English, while titles and descriptions are in Arabic. Descriptions were generated by the IMF from 2005 to 2008.
- Videocassettes and optical discs, circa 2003-2008 (Box 2-4)
  Closed. Digital use copies available within the IMF database at the Hoover Institution.
  - 35 DVDs. Primarily Legacy of Evil and Iraqi Testimonies (Box 2)
  - 20 DVDs. Primarily Legacy of Evil and Iraqi Testimonies (Box 3)
  - 1 DVD. "Remembering Saddam," by Dan North, Northstar Productions, 2004 (Box 3)
  - 2 VHS videocassettes. "The Last Jews of Baghdad," directed by Carole Basri, Adriana Davis, and Bryan, Durr, produced by D-Squared Media, 2005; and "A Show of Hands," by Northstar Productions (Box 3)
  - 2 DVCam videocassettes (Box 3)
  - 1 CD-ROM. "Selections from the North Iraq Dataset," Iraq Research and Documentation Project, 2003 (Box 3)
  - 1 CD (Box 3)
  - 7 miniDV videocassettes. Primarily Legacy of Evil and Iraqi Testimonies, also video footage of the Saddam palace and mass graves (Box 3)
  - 44 miniDV videocassettes. Primarily Legacy of Evil and Iraqi Testimonies, also video footage of the Saddam palace and mass graves (Box 4)
- Administrative records, 2003-2010; Boxes 5-7
  Closed until 2018 October 1
- Appendix: List of Iraqi Testimonies Interviewees with English subtitles, 2007-2008
  The list includes descriptions of the interviewees from the Iraqi Testimonies DVD packaging, which are listed under Iraqi Testimonies video boxed sets, but relate to all of the Iraqi Testimonies series. The descriptions in this appendix were taken essentially verbatim from the DVD packaging (some spelling errors were corrected and some proper names were standardized to a single spelling).
  Videos are in Arabic with English subtitles unless otherwise noted. Titles arranged as on the DVDs and descriptions in quotation marks taken from DVD packaging. Digital use copies are available within the IMF database at the Hoover Institution by name of the interviewee.
  - Hadi Idam Salman Al-Sultani, 2007 April 27; 14.15 minutes
    "Born in al-Mahawil in 1966. He worked for Saddam Hussein as the pilot of his private jet from 1985 to 1991. After the popular uprising in 1992 he was arrested among others; the arrested included a number of women and children. He was tortured without being interrogated or knowing why he had been arrested. He was a witness to Alfay holocaust where many of the arrested were burned alive. At the same day, he was driven to execution camps along with a group of youths and saw the execution of his brother Mahdi by fire shots. Then he was also shot and injured by some bullets, yet, he survived and managed to get away. He lived his life hiding under a pseudonym until the regime was overthrown. This Testimony was given in al-Hilla city on April 27th 2007."
  - Sami Salaman Abas, 2007 March 17; 10.24 minutes
    "Born in al-Diwaniyya in 1945. His brother is Nehma; he's a member in the Iraqi communist party. Sami was arrested in 1973 for four days only, yet he was harshly beaten and got his nose broken. He was forbidden from traveling until the regime was overthrown. He was arrested after the 1991 uprising he was severely tortured and he suffered from a head injury. He was transferred afterwards to al-Radwaniyya prison. He has many stories about the torture of the arrested there and how some of them had been thrown into the fire alive. He was released after seven months of painful torture. This Testimony was given in al-Diwaniyya."
  - Sherine Kamal Ahmed Saleh, 2006 December 16; 10.05 minutes
    "Born in al-Suleimaniyya city in 1945. A writer and a university teacher her husband is a known writer called Delshad. He was repeatedly harassed by the security agents due to the opinions his stories and poems reflected. He was discharged from the academy where he lectured and so was Sherine afterwards, the discharge lasted 3 years. Sherine refused to join al-Ba'th party and was expelled from the education body. In 1989, her husband Delshad was arrested in the university and accused of using Latin letters while teaching. Months after, she received the news of his execution. She still knew nothing about his remains when this story was filmed. This Testimony was given in al-Suleimaniyya city on December 16th, 2006."
  - Kamel S'oud Mashad Al-Jburi, 2007 April 30; 12.13 minutes
    "Born in 1951, in al-Amadiyya village, the district of Babel. He comes from a poor family of peasants comprising 15 members. He joined the communist party in 1977 and worked in the secretariat of the students' union. In 1979, a campaign was launched to eliminate the communist party and he was asked to join al-Ba'th party but when he refused, security agents tried to arrest him so he fled and hid under a pseudonym. Two years later, he was arrested but he denied his identity and name and was consequently severely tortured and was subjected to denailing. He was sentenced to death but the sentence was later reduced to life imprisonment. This Testimony was given in al-Hilla city on April 30th 2007."
  - Safa' Mahmud Afif Al-Qadi, 2007 March 14; 9.12 minutes
    "Born in al-Diwaniyya city in 1965 he is a teacher born to a communist family. After the 1991 uprising, Zuhair, his father-in-law founded a secret newspaper called 'The Truth' which was redacted at the family's house. His brother-in-law Zafer Zuhair was arrested in 1992 and executed in 1993 and his father-in-law was a wanted man. In 1994, Safa', his wife and his 8 month old daughter Fayruz were arrested along with his brother Najah, they were all taken to al-Diwaniyya's security department. Safa' and his wife were accused of harboring and hiding the father-in-law, they were severely tortured. Days later, the child Fayruz was also tortured by electric shocks which led to permanent health complications. This Testimony was given in al-Diwaniyya city on March 14th 2007."
  - Auad Sham'un Bulos Butros, 2007 January 20; 8.01 minutes
    "Born in Baghdad in 1970 he's a Christian that converted to Islam and the Shiite doctrine. As a result, he was arrested and tortured for a long time. There was no objection to his conversion to Islam but to the adoption of the Shiite confession. He was moved to Al-Rashid military hospital where a kidney of his was removed. Months later, he was moved to Abu Ghraib hospital and anesthetized, when he came round, he found that his hand was amputated. Two years later, he was released but couldn't find a proper job due to his handicap. He was arrested again in 1999, tortured and sentenced to a year in prison. This Testimony was given al-Basra city on January 20th 2007."
  - Abbas Ejteil Kavez Talal Al-Jurani, 2007 January 11; 9.39 minutes
    "Born in al-Nasiriyya city in 1951. He's a journliast and member of the communist party. He was arrested for 3 months in 1978 and placed again in custody in 1979. He was set free after months of torture. In 1980, he was arrested once again, tortured and was subjected to denailing. He was moved to the security department and transferred a year later, to the revolution court where he was sentenced to life imprisonment. He was transferred to the special sentences section in Abu Ghraib jail and released in 1983 having been granted amnesty. He was arrested again in 1994 and tortured for a whole year. He managed to leave Iraq in 1995. This testimony was given in al-Basra city on January 11th 2007."
  - Hushiar Ahmad Ali, 2006 December 7; 9.95 minutes
    In Kurdish with English subtitles. "Born in Shaqlawa city annexed to Arbil city in 1963. He lives in al-Suleimaniyya. In the early 80s his brother was killed in the bombardment that targeted the Kurdish villages. Hoshiar was arrested in 1982 when he was a student at the preparatory school. He was accused of being a member of the Kurdish national union organizations. He was severely tortured, beaten and electrified. He was sent to Shaqlawa, Arbil and al-Suleimaniyya concentration camps. Months after the arrest, he was transferred to the revolution court where he was sentenced to life imprisonment. He spent 2 years in Abu Ghraib Prison to be later released having been granted amnesty. This Testimony was given in al-Suleimaniyya city on December 7th 2006."
  - Qays Jasem Hadi, 2007 March 15; 7.65 minutes
    "Born in al-Shamiyya in 1970, in a family with an inclination towards communism, but he loved religious culture. He was arrested in 1991 after the uprising even though he did not take part in it. He was one of more than 1200 individuals that were collectively arrested. They were transferred to al-Radwaniyya prison with his brother Mohammad and their father. They went through harsh arrest circumstances suffering from beating, hunger and thirst. Qays lost 28 kgs and witnessed the death of a number of prisoners due to the bad circumstances. He was released after months of arrest and torture. This Testimony was given in al-Diwaniyya city on March 15th, 2007."
  - Dawud Salman Shehab, 2007 January 12; 12.11 minutes
    "Born in al-Basra in 1955. He's a journalist and a TV editor from a religious Muslim family. A brother of his named Wasfi was executed for allegedly being a member of the vocation party. Dawud was arrested in 1980 in al-Basra security department and severely tortured. He was forced to give an untrue statement. A year after the arrest, he was transferred to the revolution court where he was sentenced to life imprisonment. He was transferred to the Special Sentences section in Abu Ghraib jail and released 3 years later having been granted amnesty. He was arrested again in 1989 and tortured again but he was set free a year after the arrest. This Testimony was given in al-Basra city on January 12th 2007."
  - Muwafaq Makki Jasim Al-Musawi, 2007 May 30; 11.27 minutes